Okay, welcome back.
I want to start this week's videos by actually
doing a short repetition or going into a bit more
detail about some things that I think I skipped
over a bit too quickly at the end of the last
week or the last video there.
I talked about ways of defining functions,
and in particular, some syntactic constraints.
And that one might not expect for
mathematics, but in Haskell some things
are actually forbidden.
And I didn't give examples for this.
So, I want to do this now.
So, this refers to slide 68, at the end of
last week, where I talked about the uniqueness
of variable names, and that is enforced in
Haskell, and also that it's not possible in
Haskell, unlike in some more mathematical definitions
to give functions, or function definitions,
where in an argument position one has an
expression that needs computation or solving.
And one reason why I actually had this on
the slides was that in Prolog things will
be a bit different in both aspects.
So, it's better to now really emphasize this
again, and show you what exactly I mean by
things that are not allowed in Haskell.
Okay, let's start with an example.
So, first about the uniqueness of variable names.
So, we had that functions can be defined by
equations, and we had different possibilities,
we could have arguments for just variables, or
we had constants so far, we will see further
possibilities later.
But at least we had the possibility to write
something like f of zero and something else.
And for example, we also had the idea that,
or the feature that we can leave one argument
anonymous, just say something, but not give
it a variable name because we don't care.
So, something like this is perfectly okay.
Means that function f takes two arguments.
And whenever the first argument is zero, and
we don't care what the second argument is,
that's why this anonymous underscore,
and then the result is one.
Okay, so this is okay.
And then we could also say, for example, in
cases where the first argument is not zero,
but the two arguments are the same, then we
want to return two for example, right, you
could say something like, if f gets two arguments,
which are the same, so, we say something like
f of x and x, the same argument,
then the result would be two.
And maybe in all other cases, we don't care.
And they simply return three.
Yes, this would be mathematically something
that you could interpret and take as well.
If the first argument is zero, the outcome is one.
If the two arguments are the same, the outcome
is two.
In all other cases, the outcome is three.
So, this would be ... you could interpret it.
But actually, in Haskell, it's not allowed.
Yes.
And it could be made possible, but simply
the language designers decided not to have
this, mainly to avoid accidental cases.
Yes, you could always somehow
have some type constraints.
Rephrase this by something like this, so this
disallowed line could, of course, be written
like this, say, I have two arguments, x
and y, they get different variable names.
But under the condition, we use a guard, under
the condition that x is actually equal to
y, I returned a 2.
Yes, it is something that you can write and
actually that you have to write if you want
to express the thing from this line, and in
Haskell you have to write it like this, a
bit more cumbersome.
But certainly possible, and avoiding
possible ambiguities if this was simply
allowed to have the same variable name in
such a line where we decide which function
definition line to take on
what the behavior will be.
Okay, this was the first remark about the
uniqueness of variable names in defining cases.
Of course, x could be used in a different
line; that would be no contradiction.
But in the same line, we can't
use the same variable name twice.
Okay, that was the first thing and there
was this other remark about expressions in
these argument positions that are somehow
arithmetic expressions, for example, or other
expressions that require a solution,
finding or solving computation.
What do I mean by this?
Well, for example, in mathematics, something
one could also do or could imagine being valid,
something like have a function.
Now it takes only one argument.
If the argument is zero,
then I want to return a 1.
If the argument is one, then I want to return
two and maybe I have another case, like something
two times n.
So, if f is applied to the double of a number,
then for some reason this would be f of n.
And I put this in brackets even though
it wouldn't be needed, but let's be safe.
To make sure that there is not a
reason why something is fishy here.
Let's say we call f recursively on the number n
and want to add one. Yes, it would be something
like a division function.
Or actually something more
like a logarithmic function.
Yes, f 0 is one, f 1 is something else.
And f of two times n is f of n plus something.
Okay, that mathematically could be
interpreted in a reasonable way.
But again, this is not something that we can
write in Haskell the compiler would accept,
because it would mean that when you call f of
a function with a value like 15, or 16, or
whatever 20, the compiler would have to actually
perform some algebraic simplification or theorem
proving or equation solving to decide whether
or not your 15 or 16 matches this pattern.
Yes, it is of the form two times
n, and what the n actually is.
And that's not something that happens in Haskell.
Yes, in Haskell cases are more simple, you
must be able to, given the value decide
by looking at what appears in these
positions, whether it matches or not, and for
two times n that would require too much
thinking, so to speak. So it is not allowed.
In Prolog, as I said,
situations are a bit different.
And you will see this later.
But for Haskell, that's, so far, the rules.
Okay.
And then there was another thing not so much
related to things that are forbidden, but
more about when things are actually computed
also, in some corner cases (edge cases).
And I made reference to this when I
was talking about the last slide 73,
and actually, I need to look at the slides
myself to see what the definitions there were,
because I don't have them in mind.
Yes, so I had this; let me
copy this here, actually.
So, I was defining two different ways of
writing the conjunction of Boolean values.
And actually, it is predefined and uses one
of these two definitions, namely the first
one.
But one could also define the operator
oneself.
And then the two candidate definitions.
The first one was to say: Well, True and
True is certainly True, and in all
other cases the result is False.
Yes, again, with these "don't care patterns",
I'd say whatever comes here or here, the
output will be False.
Okay, and here's another version,
which was also mathematically correct.
But I mentioned that it has
slightly different behavior.
And I didn't go into detail what that is.
And I want to say a few more
words about this now instead.
Okay, so you could say if I have any Boolean,
and the second argument is True, then I cannot
as above claim that the output is True,
because the b here could be False.
But what I can say is that
b and True is definitely b.
Okay.
And I can also say that in all our cases,
is again, basically, the outcome is False.
Yes, slightly different definition
but defining the same function, y.
Where the second case will only
apply if the first case didn't apply.
And the first case only doesn't apply
if the second argument is not True.
And then, indeed, the outcomes would be False.
So, both definitions are all valid.
The second one's a bit more complicated
looking, but it's-, well, it's all the same.
Now, what's the difference
between these definitions?
I mentioned last week that there's
a difference in efficiency.
In particular, if one of the
arguments to the conjunction is a very
expensive computation.
And I can demonstrate this,
but I won't demonstrate it.
I probably won't run it, but I can use the
Ackermann function that also occurred on a
slide, namely slide 71.
And I will not repeat the
definition; it's in the slides.
The important thing to know about the Ackermann
function is that even for small inputs, it
can be very costly to compute.
So, let's actually look at
an expression like this.
False, constant False and then the thing that
we have a second argument, and again, I'll
write it in brackets, even though they wouldn't
be needed just to make sure that we are on
the same page of what the precedence relationship
between the operators and the comparison is.
So, let's say I want to compute values and the
comparison of the Ackermann function called
on values four and two. I simply want to check
that the outcome with the result of this is
greater than zero.
That will be the case, but actually, since the
compiler doesn't know what the Ackermann function
is really, this will be computed at runtime
or at compile time; then the compilation will
take very long because Ackermann of four is
already a large value with long computation.
Okay, what is the outcome of this call?
Well, of course, the outcome is False in both
cases, whether we use this or this definition;
of course, ultimately, the result will be False.
But the question is, how long will it take
to find out that the outcome is False?
Okay, let's check.
Well, let's just take the first
definition. What will happen if we take
this expression, this call,
with the first definition?
Well, what have we learned about how computation
works? We did with this factorial function.
But of course, the same rules apply here,
where we check our function definition lines
from top to bottom.
And then we see, well, let's
look at the first line.
Does it match this call?
Well, apparently not.
And how do we notice?
Well, when we check, or when the system checks
such a call against the candidate function
definition line, it looks at the arguments (in
this case, this argument and this argument)
from left to right, and sees whether they
match what's written in the function line,
the definition.
Okay, here already for the first
argument we see False is not True.
So, whatever the Ackermann function is, or the
result of the Ackermann function is, we don't
even need to check whether
its outcome is True or False.
Because already in the first argument position,
we see that False and True do not match.
So, actually, we will not use the first line.
This also means you don't have to
compute the Ackermann function.
Instead, we will switch
automatically to the second line.
And what then happens is, the first
argument is a "don't care" argument.
The second argument is a "don't care" argument
because of these two anonymous variable occurrences
up here.
So, actually, the outcome will be False; well,
this is not really surprising, of course.
But the point is, this will be without
computing the Ackermann function at all.
Yes, it is less costly because
the Ackermann function is avoided.
Okay.
However, that's only true for the
first definition of the conjunction.
Yes, of course, even for the second
definition of the conjunction, the
outcome will be False.
But it will take a very long time to compute.
Why is that?
Well, let's see; when we want to find out
whether or not this and what the outcome should
be, then we have to again compare this expression
here against the first and the second line
of our new definition of conjunction.
Let's check the first line, where we have to
check whether False could be here; the variable
could, of course, be instantiated to the
value False, so there's no reason to
reject the first line just based
on the first argument position.
So, instead, what we have to do is we also
have to look at the second position. We have
to check whether the conditions
here actually evaluate to True.
Now, to do this, we have to compute the
Ackermann function; we will get some
result, and ultimately, we will end
up, of course, computing False overall.
Because either this will be True, then we will
return the first argument, which is False;
or this call will not return True, but then it
will switch to the second line of the conjunction
and we also return False in both cases;
of course, you get False as a result.
But now the second definition, this is much more
costly because you compute the Ackermann function.
Of course, the same would be true in general,
in any programming language, right, or some
languages do have special rules for conjunction or
for "if-else" in order to avoid some computations.
And the same happens here, right?
So, we have one definition; with the first
definition above, we get these short-circuiting
semantics, where in order to compute the
conjunction, we don't always have to compute
both arguments, though the same is built
into functions in C or Java or Python.
But actually there, it needs
support from the compiler.
Here, it's simply a consequence of
how function definitions work, right?
So, there's nothing magical about the 'and' function.
All functions that you define have this feature
or this behavior, that they only compute
the argument if it's absolutely necessary.
And this depends on the definition that we
give.
And here we see that for the same function,
the conjunction, we have choices to define it
in two different ways.
And we, as programmers, can basically decide
for which cases, depending on which of the
two arguments is an expensive computation
we can avoid superfluous work.
Yes, so we don't have to
bake it into the compiler.
It depends on the way we define our functions.
It's called lazy evaluation, and we'll return
to this later, but I wanted to already point
this out, at least in this example.
Okay, and then, the other thing I want
to point out, I will do in CodeWorld.